Clay Spohn
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Clay Spohn Papers, circa 1862-1985, undated, Part 2:; (boxes 1-22, OV 23, 19.9 linear ft.)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1981, undated, 2.2:; (boxes 2-5, 4.7 linear feet)
    - Correspondence, 1925-May, 1953, undated, (37 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5461)
    - Correspondence, June, 1953-1955, (19 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5462)
    - Correspondence, 1956-July 13-16, 1958, (16 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5462)
    - Correspondence, July 13-16, 1958-June, 1963, (42 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5463)
    - Correspondence, June, 1963-April-June, 1967, (35 folders) (Box 3, Reel 5464)
    - Correspondence, April-June, 1967-October, 1969, (22 folders) (Box 3, Reel 5465)
    - Correspondence, November, 1969-February 1-10, 1970, (6 folder) (Box 4, Reel 5465)
    - Correspondence, February 1-10, 1970-April 21-30, 1971, (24 folders) (Box 4, Reel 5466)
    - Correspondence, April 21-30, 1971-January 1-19, 1973, (25 folders) (Box 4, Reel 5467)
    - Correspondence, Jan 1-19, 1973-March, 1973, (5 folders) (Box 4, Reel 5468)
    - Correspondence, April, 1973-September, 21-30, 1974, (18 folders) (Box 5, Reel 5468)
    - Correspondence, September 21-30, 1974-March-May, 1976, (22 folders) (Box 5, Reel 5469)
    - Correspondence, June 3, 1976-1981, (21 folders) (Box 5, Reel 5470)
  - Business Records, 1890-1983, 2.3:; (boxes 6-7, 1.6 linear feet)
    Business records primarily consist of Spohn's general accounting records, account books, banking records, contracts, inventories of artwork sold, records of support from the Lannan Foundation, records concerning Spohn's house in Taos, and miscellaneous receipts for healthcare, travel, art supplies, photographic services, and shipping. This subseries also includes documents concerning the companies managed by Spohn's father, John H. Spohn, and the patents and estate papers of Spohn's brother, John H. Spohn, Jr. These can be found at the beginning of the subseries.
    - John H. Spohn, 1890-1928 (Box 6, Reel unfilmed)
    - John H. Spohn, Jr., 1940-1950, (3 folders) (Box 6, Reel unfilmed)
    - General Accounts, 1950-1975, (3 folders) (Box 6, Reel unfilmed)
    - Account Books, 1932-1976, (18 books in 18 folders) (Box 6, Reel unfilmed)
    - Banking Records, 1943-1977, (28 folders) (Box 6, Reel unfilmed)
    - Contract and Financial Records (mural on Bob's Fine Food restaurant), 1945-1946 (Box 6, Reel unfilmed)
    - Contract and Consignment Records for The Little Gallery, Taos, NM, 1957 (Box 6, Reel unfilmed)
    - Inventory of Artwork in the Estate of Clay Spohn, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Reel unfilmed)
    - Records of Artwork Sold, 1941-1970 (Box 6, Reel unfilmed)
    - Records of Support from the Lannan Foundation, 1961-1962, (6 folders) (Box 7, Reel unfilmed)
    - Records of Stocks, 1939-1969 (Box 7, Reel unfilmed)
    - Insurance, 1973 (Box 7, Reel unfilmed)
    - Spohn's House in Taos, 1952-1977, (6 folders) (Box 7, Reel unfilmed)
    - Receipts, 1933-1978, (10 folders) (Box 7, Reel unfilmed)
  - Notes and Writings, 1924-1985, undated, 2.4:; (boxes 7-18, 10.8 linear feet)
    This subseries contains miscellaneous notes and writings and includes 188 notebooks, address lists, a card file of book titles, Spohn's "Subject Location," "Index and Date," and "School of Visual Arts" files, and two typescripts by other writers. The miscellaneous notes and writings, and the notebooks, are concerned with various topics, often intermingled, such as teaching notes; lists of names, books, and groceries needed; financial records for art supplies; Spohn's thoughts on philosophy and art; dietary advice; annotated studies and calculations concerning the "trisection of an arbitrary angle"; notes for his unpublished literary work "The Book," (sometimes entitled "The Actual Book" or "The Truth Book"); and brief and incomplete drafts written either for writing class assignments or for "The Book."
    Files on the School of Visual Arts contains class schedules, grade sheets, and 37 notebooks of class assignments, records of student grades, notes for lectures, lists of books for teaching, writings about teaching, and notes on art supplies for class.
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, 1924-1985, undated, (33 folders) (Box 7, Reel unfilmed)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, 1951-1958, (56 folders) (Box 8, Reel unfilmed)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, 1959-June, 1962, (57 folders) (Box 9, Reel unfilmed)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, July, 1962-May, 1970, (62 folders) (Box 10, Reel unfilmed)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, June, 1970-1985, (47 folders) (Box 11, Reel unfilmed)
    - Notebooks 1-21, 1926-1927 (Box 11, Reel unfilmed)
    - Notebooks 22-76, 1927-1962 (Box 12, Reel unfilmed)
    - Notebooks 77-105, 1962-1965 (Box 13, Reel unfilmed)
    - Notebooks 106-136, 1965-1968 (Box 14, Reel unfilmed)
    - Notebooks 137-163, 1968-1973 (Box 15, Reel unfilmed)
    - Notebooks 164-182, 1973-1976 (Box 16, Reel unfilmed)
    - Notebooks 183-188, 1976-1977 (Box 17, Reel unfilmed)
    - Address Lists, undated (Box 17, Reel 5470)
    - Card File of Book Titles, 1959-1976, (5 folders) (Box 17, Reel 5470)
    - Spohn's "Subject Location File", 1960-1961 (Box 17, Reel 5470)
    - Spohn's "Index and Date File," 1960-1961, (6 folders) (Box 17, Reel 5471)
    - Notes from Private Trade School Teacher's Course at N.Y.U., 1965, (3 folders) (Box 17, Reel 5471)
    - School of Visual Arts Notebook, 1964-1970, (11 folders) (Box 17, Reel 5471)
    - School of Visual Arts Notebook, cont., 1964-1970, (12 folders) (Box 18, Reel 5471)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1965, 1976 (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
    - Typescript, "The Sickness of American Culture" by Reinhold Niebuhr, undated (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
    - Typescript, "Clay Spohn's Museum" by Douglas Macagy, 1965? (Box 18, Reel unfilmed)
  - Artwork, 1926-1968, undated, 2.5:; (box 18, sol 22, OV 23, 0.6 linear feet)
    Artwork consists of 557 drawings, including 27 undated drawings of Washington D.C., and 14 sketchbooks.
    - Drawings (see also OV 23), 1926-1968, undated, (22 folders) (Box 18, Reel 5472)
    - Sketchbooks (see also sol 22), 1925-1939, (22 folders) (Box 18, Reel 5472)
  - Printed Material, 1894-1977, undated, 2.6:; (boxes 18-19, 1.5 linear feet)
    Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Spohn and others, exhibition prospectuses, reproductions of artwork, calendars of events, programs, brochures, books, and miscellaneous printed material.
    - Clippings, 1930-1919, undated, (2 folders) (Box 18, Reel 5472)
    - Clippings, 1941-1963, (17 folders) (Box 18, Reel 5473)
    - Clippings, 1964-1977, (8 folders) (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Spohn, 1939-1977, (4 folders) (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1940-1977, (5 folders) (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Exhibition Prospectuses, 1945-1954 (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Reproductions of Artwork, undated (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Calendars of events, 1965-1977 (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Programs, 1965-1969 (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Brochures Concerning Taos Artists, undated (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Brochures Concerning the School of Visual Arts, 1965-1969, (2 folders) (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Brochures Concerning Miscellaneous Schools, 1949-1967 (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Brochures Concerning the Oakland Museum, undated (Box 19, Reel 5473)
    - Brochures Concerning Art Supplies, 1956-1963, (3 folders) (Box 19, Reel 5474)
    - Brochures Concerning Books, 1969, undated (Box 19, Reel 5474)
    - Brochures Concerning Health, 1958-1973, (5 folders) (Box 19, Reel 5474)
    - Miscellaneous brochures, undated (Box 19, Reel 5474)
    - Book, Riverside Recipes, 1894 (Box 19, Reel 5474)
    - Book, A Poet's Breath, by Judson Crews, 1950 (Box 19, Reel 5474)
    - Book, Painting and Sculpture, Published by the San Francisco Art Association, 1952 (Box 19, Reel 5474)
    - Book, Applied Teaching Techniques by Gilbert Weaver and Louis Cenci, 1960 (Box 19, Reel 5474)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1940-1958 (Box 19, Reel 5474)
  - Photographs, circa 1862-1977, undated, 2.7:; (boxes 20-21, 0.5 linear feet)
    Photographs are of Spohn and his family, colleagues, studio, house in Taos, exhibition installations, and artwork. There are also photographs of San Francisco, including six views of damage done by the 1906 earthquake. Colleagues pictured in the photographs include Marion Karnes, Urban Neininger, Jeanne Reynal, Louis Ribak, Alfred Rogoway, and Maurice Sievan.
    Photographs of artwork for projects by Spohn picture the following: an entrance hall mural for Officers Club, San Francisco (undated); a cartoon for copper repousee sculpture for Carmel, California, Volunteer Fire Department (1936); a cartoon for copper repousee sculpture for Castro Valley Community Center (1937); a mural for Montebello, California, post office (1938); and a mural for Los Gatos Union High School (1939).
    - Spohn with Family Members, 1900-circa 1915, (2 folders) (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
    - Clay Spohn, circa 1916-1974, (4 folders) (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
    - Family Members (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
      - Spohn's Paternal Grandfather, [circa 1862], (ambrotype) (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
      - Spohn's Grandmother, undated (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
      - Spohn's Mother, undated (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
      - Spohn's Father, circa 1890-1920, (3 folders, including 7 tintypes) (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
      - Spohn's Parents, circa 1910s-1920s, (2 folders) (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
      - Spohn's Brother and Friends, circa 1910-1940, (3 folders) (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
    - Family Friends, circa 1910-1920s, (3 folders) (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
    - Bell Moose Convention, 1917 (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
    - Spohn's Colleagues, 1944-1974 (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
    - Spohn's Childhood Home, circa 1900, (2 folders) (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
    - San Francisco Earthquake Damage, 1906 (Box 20 (hol), Reel 5474)
    - From World War I, 1917 (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Travel Photographs, 1932, undated (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Views of San Francisco, 1932 (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Miscellaneous Travel Photographs, undated, (3 folders) (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Spohn's House in Taos, 1952-1970, (3 folders) (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Spohn's studio, 1977 (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Exhibition Installations, undated (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Miscellaneous Artworks by Spohn, 1936-1977, (3 folders) (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Projects, Entrance Hall Mural for Officers Club, San Francisco, undated (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Projects, Cartoon for Copper Repousee Sculpture for Carmel, California, Volunteer Fire Department, 1936 (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Projects, Cartoon for Copper Repousee Sculpture for Castro Valley Community Center, 1937 (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Projects, Mural for Montebello, California, Post Office, 1938 (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Projects, Mural for Los Gatos Union High School, 1939 (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
    - Photograph of a Painting Number 10 by Mark Rothko, undated (Box 21 (pam), Reel 5474)
  - Artifacts, undated, 2.8:; (box 21, 1 folder)
    Artifacts consist of four military pins from Marion Karnes.
    - Military pins from Marion Karnes, undated (Box 21 (pam), Reel unfilmed)